imprisoned for fraud. I was dishonest, and I paid the penalty. Before that, I'd been a practicing solicitor for 30 years. I'd had a happy and stable upbringing, a good education, a happy marriage, which, I'm pleased to say, continues. I have two adult sons. When they were growing up, I did my best to be around for them as much as I could. And I took a careful interest in what they did. I read to my boys every night, and ironically, our favorite story was "Burglar Bill." (Laughter) But when I got to prison, it soon became apparent that my background was very different to that of most of the prisoners. Few of the men that I met had had a decent education. Indeed, many associated education with humiliation and failure. I can tell you firsthand that prison is dehumanizing. Prisoners harden up, they shut down, they close in ... just to survive. And this can be devastating for families. In fact, maintaining contact with your family from prison can be very difficult indeed. And if a child does get to see their parent in prison, they have to go through the same pat-down searches as the adults. They walk through the same detector frames, they're sniffed by the same sniffer dogs, and all because some children have been the unwitting carriers of drugs and mobile phones. And when they get through to see their parent, they may be tired from a long journey, shy, tongue-tied, even upset. And it isn't easy for the parents, who may not be getting along. For many reasons, not just these, over half of prisoners lose contact with their children and families. How can we help prisoners to stay in contact with their families? When I was a prisoner at Channings Wood Prison, I began working for a charity called Storybook Dads. Storybook Dads began in 2003, when Sharon Berry, a civilian worker in a prison, realized just how much many prisoners wanted to stay in contact with their children. And so, armed with a few storybooks, she began to help prisoners to read and record stories to send home to their children. It wasn't a new idea. Few ideas like this are new. They're great ideas. But it was an instant success. You may wonder: How does the recording of the stories work in prison? Is it difficult for prisoners? Can it be challenging? Well, the process of choosing, reading and recording a story can be very challenging for prisoners. Prison is tough, and prisoners can't afford to show any signs of weakness or vulnerability. But this, this recording process, this can be uncomfortable, upsetting, sometimes all just a bit too much. And prisoners often cry. They cry because they regret missing out on their children's lives. They cry because they're ashamed that they've let their families down. They cry because they don't know how to go about reading to their children. But because when they come to us we offer a private space, one-to-one, prisoners don't need to be tough anymore, and they can use their vulnerability as a strength when contacting with their children. I remember one prisoner who came to record. He was a big, hard man with a reputation for being tough. He came along as implacable as ever. But when the door of the recording room closed behind him, that facade began to crumble. From his pocket, he took a screwed-up piece of paper and quietly began to read the words which he'd written as a message for his two little ones. His hands were shaking. And then, in a surprisingly quiet voice, he began to sing their favorite lullaby. You see, there wasn't much that he could do from behind bars to show his children that he missed and loved them. But he could do this. Once the recording is made, it's sent to the Storybook Dads production unit at Channings Wood Prison in Devon. And that's where I worked. I was trained, along with other prisoners, to edit and produce recordings sent in from prisons all over the United Kingdom. Using audio and video software, the recordings have the mistakes taken out and sound effects and music added in. And the experience and skill which the prison editors gain helps them in their future employment. Once the recording is finalized, it's transferred to a CD or a DVD and sent out to the families so that the children can watch them whenever they feel the need. And they listen to these recordings and watch them a lot -- at bedtime, in the car ... Some even take them to school to show their friends. These recordings, they show the children that they're loved and missed. And they show the prisoner that they can do something for their child, as a parent. Do you remember Sophie? Well, one day, just before Christmas, a parcel arrived, and this is what was in it. Let's listen to a little of it together. (Video) Santa: On, Comet! On, Cupid! On, Donner and Blitzen! Charlie: That's his reindeer, isn't it? Santa: It is his reindeer, yeah. Up, up, higher and higher they flew, across land, across oceans they sped. Through the magical northern lights they passed -- I'd love to see the northern lights, wouldn't you? Charlie: I figure they'd probably look a bit like that snowman's belly. Santa: They probably would, yeah. That's a cool snowman, isn't it? Charlie: It's very cool indeed, I love it. Santa: They visited all the children in the world and left presents for each and every one. In the blink of an eye, they were back in Frogsbottom Field. (Charlie Laughs) Santa: You think that's well funny? Charlie: I want to live in Frogsbottom Field! Santa: Where do you live, in Frogsbottom Tree? Charlie: I don't, I live in this tree. I've made it all Christmasy-look. Santa: It's nice, that. You've done a good job, good job. Charlie: Thank you very much! (Laughter) Alan Crickmore: Sophie and her mum listened to that three times, and they haven't laughed so much in a long time. They can see that he's all right, they can see that he loves them, and the next time he rings, Sophie's got plenty to talk about: "What does Charlie the Chimp eat? Will daddy do another story very soon?" Since it began in 2003, Storybook Dads has grown and grown. It now operates as Storybook Dads and Storybook Mums in more than 100 prisons in the United Kingdom. Ninety-eight percent of the prisoners who take part say that it's improved their relationship with their child. And since 2003, over 60,000 DVDs and CDs have been sent out to the children of prisoners. For Sophie's family and for thousands of families like them, Storybook Dads has been a lifeline. Some prisoners say that it's the first time that they've begun to build a relationship with their child. And some poor readers have been so inspired by what they've been able to achieve that they've gone to education classes to improve their own reading skills. Let's go back to the story of "The Ugly Duckling." But this time, I'd like to play you a recording made by a prisoner, because it encapsulates the power of what we do. The prisoner was an Irish Traveller who couldn't read. And he wanted to send a story home to his daughter for her birthday. With the help of a mentor and some clever editing, something magical happened. This is an extract from the raw recording, where the prisoner is reading the story by repeating it, phrase at a time. (Audio) Mentor: He had nowhere to hide. Owen: He had nowhere to hide. Mentor: So one day, he ran away. Owen: Then one day, he ran away. Mentor: He ran until he came to the great marsh. Owen: He run until he come to the great marsh. Mentor: Where the wild ducks lived. Owen: Where the wild ducks lived. AC: And this is a recording -- an excerpt of the recording with the mentor's voice taken out and sound effects and music added in. (Audio) Owen: He had nowhere to hide. Then one day, he run away. He run until he come to the great marsh where the wild ducks lived, and he laid in the rushes for two weeks. (Music) (Ducks quack) Some wild ducks and geese come to look at him. "You're very ugly," they said, and they laughed at him. (Ducks quack) The ugly duckling ran away from the great marsh. (Duck quacks) AC: And this is how he finished the story: (Audio) Owen: He wasn't an ugly duckling at all. During the winter, he had grown into a beautiful white swan. The other swans looked at him and thought how beautiful he was. "Come with us," they said. And he did. (Bird sounds) Well, Tiara, I hope you have enjoyed this story as much as I enjoyed reading this story to you. I cannot wait to be with you again and hold you in my arms. All my love, your daddy, Owen. Lots of love, I miss you with all my heart. Goodbye for now, my love. Bye bye. (Music) (Music ends) AC: When he listened to that recording in his cell before it was sent out to his daughter, he cried. And that's a pretty common reaction from prisoners, as they realize for the first time they've been able to do something for their child which they never thought they could. They've connected in the most fundamental way, through the medium of storytelling. And as for Sophie, she wants "The Gruffalo" next time. (Laughter) (Applause)
emprisonné pour fraude. J’ai été malhonnête, et j'en ai payé le prix. Avant cela, j'avais été avocat pendant 30 ans. J'avais eu une enfance heureuse et stable, une bonne éducation, un mariage heureux qui, par bonheur, continue. J'ai deux fils adultes. Quand ils étaient petits, j'ai fait de mon mieux pour être auprès d'eux le plus possible. Et je faisais attention à ce qu'ils faisaient. Tous les soirs, je lisais une histoire à mes garçons, et, ironie du sort, notre livre préféré était « Bill, le voleur ». (Rires) Mais, une fois en prison, il m'est vite apparu évident que mon éducation était très différente de celle de la plupart des détenus. Peu d'entre eux avaient reçu une éducation décente. Pour beaucoup, l'éducation était synonyme d'humiliation et d'échec. Pour l'avoir vécu, je peux vous dire que la prison déshumanise. Les détenus se durcissent, se renferment sur eux-mêmes, juste pour survivre. Et cela peut être dévastateur pour les familles. De fait, garder le contact avec votre famille depuis une prison peut être vraiment très difficile. Et si un enfant arrive à voir ses parents en prison, il doit être fouillé comme les adultes. Il franchit les mêmes portiques de sécurité. Il est reniflé par les mêmes chiens. Tout ça parce que des enfants ont été utilisés comme passeurs. Quand ces enfants arrivent enfin au parloir, ils sont peut-être fatigués d'un long voyage, timides, muets, peut-être même contrariés. Et ce n'est pas facile pour les parents, qui ne s'entendent peut-être pas. Pour de nombreuses raisons, plus de la moitié des détenus perdent contact avec leur famille. Comment peut-on aider les détenus à rester en contact avec leur famille ? Quand j’étais détenu à Channings Woods, j'ai travaillé pour une association nommée Storybook Dads. Storybook Dads a débuté en 2003 quand Sharon Berry, une bénévole, a réalisé à quel point les détenus souhaitaient rester en contact avec leurs enfants. Et donc, armée de quelques livres pour enfants, elle aida les détenus à lire et à enregistrer des histoires pour les envoyer à leurs enfants. Ce n’était pas une idée nouvelle. Peu d’idées comme celle-ci sont nouvelles. Ce sont des idées géniales. Mais ce fut un succès immédiat. Vous vous demandez peut-être comment fonctionnent ces enregistrements ? Est-ce difficile pour les détenus ? Cela peut-il être éprouvant ? Le processus de choisir, de lire et d'enregistrer l'histoire peut être très éprouvant pour les détenus. La prison est difficile à vivre, et les détenus ne peuvent pas se permettre de se montrer faibles ou vulnérables. Mais ce processus d'enregistrement peut mettre mal à l'aise, contrarier, parfois même sembler un peu trop. Et souvent les détenus pleurent. Ils pleurent parce qu'ils regrettent de manquer la vie de leurs enfants. Ils pleurent parce qu'ils ont honte d'avoir laissé tomber leur famille. Ils pleurent parce qu'ils ne savent pas comment lire à leurs enfants. Mais parce qu'on leur offre un espace privé lorsqu'ils viennent, en tête à tête, les détenus n'ont plus besoin de se montrer fort, et ils peuvent utiliser leur vulnérabilité comme une force quand ils parlent à leurs enfants. Je me souviens d'un détenu qui était venu enregistrer. C’était un homme grand et fort, avec la réputation d’être dur. Il est venu, aussi implacable que d'habitude. Mais lorsque la porte du studio d'enregistrement s'est refermée, cette façade a commencé à s’effriter Il a pris un papier chiffonné dans sa poche et il a commencé doucement à lire ce qu'il avait écrit pour ses deux petits. Ses mains tremblaient. Et d'une voix étonnamment douce, il a commencé à chanter leur berceuse préférée. Il ne pouvait pas faire grand-chose de derrière les barreaux pour montrer à ses enfants qu'ils lui manquaient, mais ça, il pouvait le faire. Une fois l'enregistrement terminé, il est envoyé au service de production de Storybook Dads à la prison de Channings Wood, dans le comté de Devon. Et c'est là où j'ai travaillé. J'ai été formé avec d'autres détenus à éditer et à produire des enregistrements provenant de prisons de tout le Royaume-Uni. Au moyen de logiciels audio et vidéo, on enlève les défauts des enregistrements et on y ajoute des bruitages et de la musique. Et l’expérience et les compétences que les éditeurs-détenus en retirent les aident pour leurs futurs emplois. Une fois l'enregistrement finalisé, il est transféré sur un CD ou un DVD et envoyé à la famille pour que les enfants puissent le voir dès qu'ils en ressentent le besoin. Et ils écoutent et regardent beaucoup ces enregistrements. Au coucher, dans la voiture... Certains les emmènent même à l’école pour montrer à leurs amis. Ces enregistrements montrent aux enfants qu'ils sont aimés et manquent à leur parent. Et ils montrent au détenu qu'ils peuvent faire quelque chose pour leur enfant, en tant que parent. Vous vous souvenez de Sophie ? Eh bien, un jour, juste avant Noël, un colis arriva. Voici ce qu'il y avait dedans. Écoutons ensemble. (Vidéo) Père Noël : C'est parti, Comet ! Cupid ! Donner et Blitzen ! Charlie: Ce sont ses rennes, c'est ça? Père Noël: Oui, c'est ça. Plus haut, plus haut, ils volèrent, à travers terres et mers, ils se dépêchèrent. À travers les magiques aurores boréales, ils passèrent - J'adorerais voir une aurore boréale. Pas toi ? Charlie : Oui, ça doit ressembler un peu au ventre de ce bonhomme de neige. Père Noël : Probablement, oui. Cool, ce bonhomme de neige, non ? Charlie : Super cool, oui. J'adore. Père Noël : Ils visitèrent tous les enfants du monde et laissèrent des cadeaux à chacun d'eux. En un instant, ils étaient de retour à Grenouilly-les-Prés. Charlie : (Rires) Père Noël : Tu trouves ça drôle ? Charlie : Oui. Je veux vivre là-bas. Père Noël : Où vis-tu ? À Grenouilly-l'Arbre ? Charlie : Oh non... Je vis dans cet arbre. Je l'ai décoré pour Noël. Regarde. Père Noël : C'est beau. Tu as très bien travaillé. Charlie : Merci beaucoup. (Rires de l'audience) Alan Crickmore : Sophie et sa mère l'ont écouté trois fois, et elles n'avaient pas ri autant depuis bien longtemps. Elles peuvent voir qu'il va bien, qu'il les aime. Et au prochain coup de fil, Sophie aura plein de choses à dire : « Que mange Charlie le Chimpanzé ? » « Est-ce que Papa enverra bientôt une autre histoire ? » Depuis sa création en 2003, Storybook Dads s'est développé. Désormais, Storybook Dads et Storybook Mums (pour les mamans) opèrent dans plus de cent prisons du Royaume-Uni. 98 % des prisonniers qui participent disent que cela a amélioré leur relation avec leur enfant. Et depuis 2003, plus de 60 000 DVDs et CDs ont été envoyés aux enfants de détenus. Pour la famille de Sophie et pour des milliers d'autres comme elle, Storybook Dads est une bouée de sauvetage. Des détenus disent que c'est la première fois qu'ils ont commencé à construire une relation avec leur enfant. Certains qui lisaient difficilement ont été tellement inspirés par ce dont ils étaient capables qu'ils ont pris des cours pour s’améliorer en lecture. Revenons à l'histoire du Vilain petit canard. Mais là, j'aimerais vous faire écouter un enregistrement fait par un détenu. Parce que ça résume le pouvoir de ce que nous accomplissons. Le détenu était un gitan irlandais qui ne savait pas lire, il voulait envoyer une histoire chez lui pour l'anniversaire de sa fille. Avec l'aide d'un mentor, et d'un montage astucieux, il s'est produit quelque chose de magique. Ceci est un extrait de l'enregistrement de base où le détenu lit l'histoire en répétant phrase par phrase. (Audio) Mentor : Il ne pouvait se cacher. Owen : Il ne pouvait se cacher. Mentor : Alors un jour, il s'enfuit. Owen : Puis un jour, il s'enfuit. Mentor : Il courut jusqu'au grand marais. Owen : Il courut jusqu'au grand marais. Mentor : Où vivaient les canards sauvages. Owen : Où vivaient les canards sauvages. Et ceci est un extrait d'enregistrement où l'on a retiré la voix du mentor et ajouté des bruitages et de la musique. (Audio) Owen : Il ne pouvait se cacher. Donc un jour, il a fui. Il a couru jusqu'au grand marais où vivaient les canards sauvages. Il est resté allongé dans les roseaux deux semaines. (Musique) (Cris d'oies) Des canards sauvages et des oies vinrent pour le voir. « Tu es vraiment laid », lui dirent-ils, et ils se moquèrent de lui. (Caquètements) Le vilain petit canard s'enfuit du grand marais. AC : Et voici comment il termine l'histoire. (Audio) Il n’était pas un vilain petit canard. Durant l'hiver, il s’était transformé en un beau cygne blanc. Les autres cygnes le regardèrent constatant à quel point il était beau. « Viens avec nous », dirent-ils. Et c'est ce qu'il fit. (Cris d'oiseaux) (Musique) Eh bien Tiara, j’espère que tu as aimé cette histoire, autant que j'ai aimé te la lire. J'ai hâte d’être à nouveau avec toi et de te prendre dans mes bras. Avec tout mon amour, ton papa, Owen. Plein d'amour. Tu me manques énormément. Au revoir, mon cœur. Au revoir. (Musique) (Fin de la musique) AC : Quand il a écouté l'enregistrement avant qu'il ne soit envoyé à sa fille, il a pleuré. C'est une réaction assez fréquente chez les détenus, lorsqu'ils réalisent pour la première fois qu'ils ont fait quelque chose pour leur enfant qu'ils n'auraient jamais pensé pouvoir faire. Ils ont établi une connexion de la façon la plus fondamentale au moyen d'une histoire. Quant à Sophie, elle veut Gruffalo la prochaine fois. (Rires) (Applaudissements)